Guide to the Bernard Augustine De Voto Papers, 1885-1974
Department of Special Collections
Bernard Augustine De Voto Papers,
1885-1974
Special Collections M0242
De Voto, Bernard Augustine, 1897-1955
6 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
None.
Provenance
Gift of Wallace Stegner, 1973.
Biographical Note
Bernard Augustine DeVoto, born in Ogden, Utah in 1897, received his early education in Utah and graduated from Harvard in 1920. He taught English and creative writing at Northwestern and Harvard Universities. DeVoto was a novelist, historian, critic, editor, and a vigorous exponent of government conservation of natural resources. He died in 1955.
Scope and Contents
Collection includes: 1)correspondence to and from Bernard DeVoto and to and from Avis DeVoto and other miscellaneous correspondents including Wallace Stegner and Carl Brandt, 2) financial papers such as cash account books, tax returns, receipts, 3) legal agreements, contracts and other documentations, 4) newsclippings, magazine articles and magazines, 5) photographs and 6) xeroxes of correspondence, newsclippings, magazine articles.
Container List
- CORRESPONDENCE - OUTGOING (FROM DEVOTO) & INCOMING (TO DEVOTO):
  - Outgoing correspondence: 1919, 1922, 1935-1936, 37 1938, 1940, 1943-1945, 1947-1948, 1951-1953. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Outgoing correspondence - 1954-1955. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- INCOMING CORRESPONDENTS: 1) Associated American Artists Galleries, 2) Bantam Workshop, 3) Benjamin Franklin Magazine Awards, 4) Carl Brandt, 5) Collier's, 6) Ford Times, 7) Harcourt Brace & Co., 8) Houghton Mifflin Co., 9) House of Whittmore, 10) Internal Revenue Service - Treasury Dept., 11) The Lamp, 12) W. Colston Leigh, 13) Gordon Manning, 14) National Geographic Society, 15) New York Times, 16) Albert R. Perkins.
  - Incoming correspondence - 1938, 1944, 1947, 1948, 1950 - 1952. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Incoming correspondence - 1953. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Incoming correspondence- 1954. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Incoming correspondence - 1955. (Box 1, Folder 6)
- CORRESPONDENCE - MISCELLANEOUS:
  - 1937, 1940, 1945, 1947, 1951, 1952. (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - 1953. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - 1954. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - 1955. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1956-1961. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1962, 1968, 1969. (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1970 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 1971 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 1972-1973 & No date, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- FINANCIAL PAPERS
  - Miscellaneous papers re: finances and taxes. (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Cash account books: 1945-1948, 1950-1952. (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Royalty Statements: 1943-1944, 1946-1948, 1951-1952: (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Little, Brown & Co.; Houghton Mifflin Co.; Harvard University Press.
  - Tax returns and related notes: 1932-1935, 1937-1938, 1940-1947, 1950-1952. (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Legal documents: (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - 1. Decree of Divorce - Dec.28, 1885.Rhoda DeWolf vs. Edward S. De Wolf. DS.
    - 2. Agreement between DeVoto and MacMillan Co., April 5, 1935re: Chariot of Fire & The House of Sun-Goes-Down.
    - 3. Agreement between DeVoto and Harcourt Brace & Co., Inc., Jan. 12, 1950.DS.
    - 4. Agreement by the Curtis Publishing Co. re: the book Shall We Let the Dam-Builders Ruin Our National Parks, May 31, 1950.
    - 5. Agreement between DeVoto and Houghton Mifflin Co. re: Lewis & Clark Journals, July 7, 1952.
    - 6. Will and testament - Avis M. DeVoto.
    - 7. Will and testament - Bernard DeVoto, (two copies).
    - 8. Affidavit and claim for additional travel pay, June 14, 1918.
    - 9. Certificate appointing DeVoto to the rank of 2nd Lieutenant of Infrantry, Aug. 26, 1918.DS.
    - 10. Certificate of Baptism - Bernard DeVoto - March 7, 1940.DS.
    - 11. Certificate - Central Officers' Training School, Camp Lee, Virginia - Bernard DeVoto. DS.
    - 12. Certificate of Death - Bernard DeVoto - Jan. 16, 1956.
    - 13. Certificate of Marriage - Florian B. DeVoto & Rhoda D. DeWolf. Oct. 6, 1895.DS.
  - Photographs - see also 1/180/14 and 1/182/3 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Miscellaneous: the items listed below are only those which are of special interest. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - 1. Bernard A. DeVoto - Recollection and Appreciation by Darrell J. Greenwell., 4pp.
    - 2. Review of The Crooked Mile in the New York Times Book Review, Oct. 5, 1924.Typescript., 2pp. (two copies).
    - 3. Donner Pass by Bernard DeVoto., 2pp.
    - 4. Proposal for an Article on the White Mountain National Forest, in New Hampshire., 2pp. (two copies).
    - 5. Biographical information re: DeVoto by W.E.H. Higman., 17pp.
  - Tape recordings (10) (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - The Syllabus - Northwestern University Yearbook. (Box 3, Folder 23a)
  - Magazine clippings: clippings of articles by DeVoto. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Newsclippings (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Newsclippings and magazine clippings re: The Year of Decision. (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Newsclippings re: Mark Twain. (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Newsclippings - Chicago reviews mainly from Evanston News (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Books & reports: (Box 4, Folder 29)
    - 1. Reports by Lawrence S. Kubie: a) A Doctorate in Psychotherapy..., b) The Fallacious Use of Quantitative Concepts in Dynamic Psychology, c) The Forgotten Man of Education, d) The Fundamental Nature of the Distinction Between Normality and Neurosis, e) The Half-Failure of the Full-Time System as an Instrument of Medical Education, f) The Repetitive Core of Neurosis, g) Social Forces and the Neurotic Process.
    - 2. Kubie, Lawrence S. Neurotic Distortion of the Creative Process, The Noonday Press, 1958.
    - 3. School Yearbook: Souvenir Edition - Classicum, Ogden High School, 1914 -Ogden, Utah.
  - Magazines: (Box 4, Folder 30)
    - 1) Current Opinion Vol. LXXV, No. 4, Oct. 1923
    - 2) Dialogue, reprint from Vol. VI, No. 3 & 4, Autumn and Winter, 1971
    - 3) Harper's Magazine, reprint from Dec. 1949
    - 4) Ford Times, Vol. 48, No. 5, May 1956, (two copies)
    - 5) Ford Times, Vol. 48, No. 6, June 1956
    - 6) The Griffin, Vol. 5, No. 2, Feb. 1956,(signed cover note from Arthur Schlesinger Jr.)
    - 7) Harper's Magazine, Vol. 209, No. 1241, Aug. 1954.
  - Magazines: (Box 4, Folder 31)
    - 1) Lincoln and Mercury Times Vol. 8, No. 2, March - April 1956
    - 2) The Louisiana Purchase by DeVoto, reprint from Collier's Magazine
    - 3) Nature Magazine, Vol. 49, No.4, April 1956
    - 4) New England Journeys, Number 2, Ford Times special edition, 1954.
    - 5) Nieman Reports, Vol. X, No. 1, Jan. 1956
    - 6) The Progressive, Vol. 20, No. 1, Jan. 1956
    - 7) New York Times Book Review, Feb. 10, 1974
  - Theme papers - typed: written by Sarah Boyden (Brown) for DeVoto's class - English D-6, some of the papers contain lengthy comments by DeVoto. (Box 4, Folder 32)
- XEROX COPIES
  - Correspondence: 1916, 1918, 1920, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence: 1922, 1923, 1925 - 1929 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence: 1930 - 1938 (Box 5, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence: 1940 - 1945 (Box 5, Folder 36)
  - Correspondence: 1946 - 1947 Jan. (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Correspondence: Feb. 1947 - Mar. 1947 (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Correspondence: April 1947 - May 1947 (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - Correspondence: June 1947 - Aug. 1947 (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Correspondence: Sept. 1947 - Nov. 1947 (Box 6, Folder 41)
  - Correspondence: Dec. 1947 - Jan. 1948 (Box 6, Folder 42)
  - Correspondence: Feb. 1948 - March 1948 (Box 6, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence: April 1948 - May 1948 (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Correspondence: June 1948 (Box 7, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence: July 1948 - Aug. 1948 (Box 7, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence: Sept. 1948 - Oct. 1948 (Box 7, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence: Nov. 1948 - Dec. 1948 (Box 7, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence: Jan. 1949 - Mar. 1949 (Box 7, Folder 49)
  - Correspondence: April 1949 - June 1949 (Box 7, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence: July 1949 - Oct. 1949 (Box 7, Folder 51)
  - Correspondence: Nov. 1949 - Jan. 1950 (Box 8, Folder 52)
  - Correspondence: Feb. 1950 - April 1950 (Box 8, Folder 53)
  - Correspondence: May 1950 - May 1951 (Box 8, Folder 54)
  - Correspondence: Aug. 1951 - April 1953(no correspondence for June & July of 1951) (Box 8, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence: May 1953 - Dec. 1954 (Box 8, Folder 56)
  - Correspondence: Jan. 1955 - Nov. 1955 (Box 8, Folder 57)
  - Correspondence: 1956, 1961 - 1963, 1969 - 1970 & No Date (Box 8, Folder 58)
  - Correspondence: A Closed Door: Letters from Bernard Augustine DeVoto to Katharine Becker - March 1919 - December 1920. (Box 9, Folder 59)
  - Correspondence: between DeVoto & Nethercot & Stegner. (Box 9, Folder 60)
  - Correspondence: between Frost, Robert & DeVoto (Box 9, Folder 61)
  - Correspondence: between Higman, W.E. and Stegner, Wallace (Box 9, Folder 62)
  - Correspondence: between Arthur Schlesinger Jr. and DeVoto (Box 9, Folder 63)
  - Magazine articles: 1924 - 1928 (Box 9, Folder 64)
  - Magazine articles: 1929 - 1933 (Box 9, Folder 65)
  - Magazine articles: 1934 - 1937 (Box 9, Folder 66)
  - Magazine articles: 1938 - 1940 (Box 10, Folder 67)
  - Magazine articles: 1941 - 1943 (Box 10, Folder 68)
  - Magazine articles: 1944 - 1946 (Box 10, Folder 69)
  - Magazine articles: 1947 - 1949 (Box 10, Folder 70)
  - Magazine articles: 1950 - 1952 (Box 10, Folder 71)
  - Magazine articles: 1953 - 1954 (Box 10, Folder 72)
    May 1955 - DeVoto Near England
  - Magazine articles: 1955 - 1956, 1965 (Box 10, Folder 73)
    1955 Lewis & Clark expedition pamphlet by DeVoto
  - Reviews of DeVoto's books. (Box 11, Folder 74)
  - The Crumb -- Breadloaf Writers' Conference, 1932 - 1936 (Box 11, Folder 75)
  - The Crumb -- Breadloaf Writers' Conference, 1937 - 1939 (Box 11, Folder 76)
  - The Crumb -- Breadloaf Writers' Conference, 1941, 1947 - [UNK] (Box 11, Folder 77)
  - Middlebury College Bulletin re: Breadloaf Writers' Conference. (Box 11, Folder 78)
  - Bernard DeVoto and the Mormon Tradition by Leland Fetzer. (Box 11, Folder 79)
  - List of the Hiller Photograph Albums I, II, III, IV, & V of the Powell Survey. (Box 11, Folder 80)
  - Bibliography index re: DeVoto (Box 11, Folder 81)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 11, Folder 82)
  - correspondence re: DeVoto's medical history. Correspondence is mostly between DeVoto and Dr. I. Herbert Scheinberg re: DeVoto's Medical problems. This section also includes autopsy reports and news-clippings. (Box 12)
    not on Shelf on 5/3/84 CR